<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the divorce of Henry VIII and Katharine of Arragon with the defence of Sanders, the refutation of the two first books of The history of the reformation of Dr. Burnett / by Joachim le Grand ; with Dr. Burnett's answer and vindication of himself.</title>
            <title>Histoire du divorce de Henry VIII, roy d'Angleterre, et de Catherine d'Arragon. English</title>
            <author>Le Grand, Joachim, 1653-1733.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50025</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254492</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50025)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 153:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the divorce of Henry VIII and Katharine of Arragon with the defence of Sanders, the refutation of the two first books of The history of the reformation of Dr. Burnett / by Joachim le Grand ; with Dr. Burnett's answer and vindication of himself.</title>
                  <title>Histoire du divorce de Henry VIII, roy d'Angleterre, et de Catherine d'Arragon. English</title>
                  <author>Le Grand, Joachim, 1653-1733.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Histoire du divorce de Henry VIII, roy d'Angleterre, et de Catherine d'Arragon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  VIII, --  King of England, 1491-1547.</term>
               <term>Catharine, --  of Aragon, Queen, consort of Henry VIII, King of England, 1485-1536.</term>
               <term>Sander, Nicholas, 1530?-1581. --  De origine ac progressu schismatis Anglicani.</term>
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715. --  History of the reformation of the Church of England.</term>
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715. --  Letter to Monsieur Thevenot.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57293:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57293:1"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ry of the Divorce of <hi>HENRY</hi> VIII. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> KATHARINE</hi> of ARRAGON.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſence of <hi>Sanders.</hi> The Refutation of the Two firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he Hiſtory of the Reformation of Dr. <hi>Burnett.</hi> By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Grand.</hi> With Dr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s Anſwer and Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf.</head>
               <p>WEE have not as yet ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more than the firſt Part of this Work, which was publiſhed the Fifth of this Month. I know not whether a Man may judge of the two other Parts by this, which ſeems at firſt but an Abridgement of the two firſt Books of the Hiſtory of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> though the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor promiſes to refute them in the two following Volumes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It ſeems that <hi>M. le Grand</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that Men would have this Idea of his Work, which is the Reaſon he has put before that Hiſtory a <hi>preliminary</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, where he endeavours, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out telling his Deſign, to divert the Reader from having any ſuch Thoughts. He relates at firſt a Conference that he had with Dr. <hi>Burnett,</hi> in the King's Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, in the Preſence of M. <hi>Thevenot,</hi> and M. <hi>Auzout.</hi> The Makers of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues frequently introduce two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, one of which puts the Queſtion, and the other Anſwers: One is the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the other is the Scholar: Or at leaſt, they make him more learned that teaches, than he that propounds the Difficulties. But in the Relation of this Conference we find quite the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Mr. <hi>Burnett,</hi> who, according to the Authors Character, is a Perſon of a quick peircing Wit, laborious, indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable, and moſt capable to defend the Reformation; whoſe Expreſſions are always free, bold and full of fire; and who ſpeaks upon this Occaſion with an Eloquence that charms them that hear him: Yet this Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi> leaves the principal Points undetermined, or elſe conſents and ſubmits every thing that is oppoſed againſt him. But <hi>M. Le Grand,</hi> who <hi>propounds his Difficulties af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a plain humble Manner, and rather as Doubts than as real Objections, makes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, quotes, attacks, and at length</hi> leaves Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi> with hardly a Word to ſay for himſelf.</p>
               <p>There is no Wonder to be made, that ſo ſoon, as M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to write, he ſhould ſo ſuddainly overturn a Man of that Learning and Reputation as Dr. <hi>Burnett.</hi> For though <hi>never any Man wrote with more Cunning, or knew better how to link and chain one Event to another; yet,</hi> as the Author ſays,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57293:2"/>
                  <hi>he never ſtudied the Hiſtory of</hi> England. He that romaged all the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Libraries of the Kingdom, to fetch out Regiſters and authentick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords and Acts, and Copies of Diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Memoirs and other Manuſcripts of thoſe times, out of which to compoſe his Hiſtory; who has printed a Volume in Folio of thoſe ſort of Pieces, in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of what he ſays; he to whom the whole Nation, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it ſelf, gave publick Teſtimonies of the Eſteem which they had for his Work. But the Reaſon that M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> alledges for his Adverſary's Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the Hiſtory, is becauſe he does not refute the Errors which M. <hi>Varillas</hi> has committed in ſeveral Things that concern'd <hi>England,</hi> in his firſt Book of the Hiſtory of Hereſy; having no other Deſign than to criticize upon the Ninth, which only relates to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as appears by the Title, <hi>A Critick upon the Ninth Book of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of M.</hi> Varillas, <hi>where he ſpeaks of the Revolutions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi> and M. <hi>Varillas</hi> being ſuch defective Hiſtorians in M. <hi>Le Grand</hi>'s Opinion, there is no Wonder if he threaten them, <hi>to raiſe up a Third, that ſhall make them loſe a good Part of the Reputation which they have gotten.</hi> And that which confirms his Hopes is this, becauſe 'tis Plain, <hi>That thoſe Authors are very Negligent, and that their laſt Works are leſs valuable than their first.</hi> As for M. <hi>Varillas,</hi> ſince it could never be believed that a Hiſtorian, ſo partial, could write after a rational manner, I never gave my ſelf the Trouble to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his Works together; and ſo I cannot ſay whether his Anſwer to his Adverſaries <hi>Critick,</hi> be better or worſe than his Hiſtories. But as for Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nett</hi>'s Travels into <hi>Italy,</hi> I muſt take the Liberty to inform the Publick, that M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> who cites that Book to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what he writes, made his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the French Verſion, though Mr. <hi>Burnet</hi> hath declared, <hi>That he had but too frequently miſtook his Meaning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Memoirs which the Author made uſe of, he ſays nothing but what he has taken out of the Letters and Diſpatches of <hi>Francis</hi> I. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. the Cardinals, <hi>Woolſey</hi> and <hi>Grandemont,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Auxerres, Maion, Tarbes, &amp;c.</hi> Where we find that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> makes two Perſons of Cardinal <hi>Grandemont</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Tarbes,</hi> whereas they were but one and the ſame. As for the Letters and Diſpatches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and Cardinal <hi>Wolſey,</hi> a great many of them being in Engliſh, as may be ſeen in Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s Collection, perhaps they might be of little Uſe to our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; for we are apt to believe that he did not underſtand the Language; as well for that by the Judgment which he makes of the <hi>Travels into</hi> Italy, as by what Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi> ſhews in the Letter which follows this Extract, it appears that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> never caſt his Eyes upon that Collection of Pieces which is added to the Engliſh Edition of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Reformation of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Divorce of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. is too well known to make an Extract of it. We ſhall therefore make ſome Remarks, which will abſolutely unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe who may imagine that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi>'s Book is an Abſtract of one part of Mr. <hi>Burnett</hi>'s. In ſhort, the Method and Deſign of thoſe Two Books is extreamly different, as well as the Memoirs upon which they are ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57293:2"/>1. M. <hi>Burnet</hi> has no other Aim in Writing the Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. than to repreſent how the Proceedings of that Prince, whoſe irregular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct he does not undertake to juſtify, levelled the Way to that Reformation which was made under his Succeſſors: M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> makes <hi>Henry</hi> to be always in the wrong, as if he had never done good. 2. M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> beſtows his Encomiums upon thoſe that he thinks deſerve them, though never ſo great Enemies of the Reformation, as <hi>Fiſher, More</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Poole.</hi> He never diſſembles the Faults of thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed moſt to the Reformation, as <hi>Cromwell, Cranmer,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, &amp;c.</hi> becauſe he has obſerved by an infinite Number of Examples out of ſacred and eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, That God never makes uſe of perfect Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the Execution of his Deſigns. M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> ſeems to have had very oppoſite Ends. All thoſe that contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to advance the Reformation are very ill handled by him in his Hiſtory; where he gives them the honourable Title of <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> particularly to <hi>Ann Bolen,</hi> and <hi>Cranmer,</hi> whom he calls the <hi>Falſe Prelate;</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> whom he abuſes, <hi>as Man as ignorant as ever was in the World.</hi> This Miniſter, who is never permitted to juſtify himſelf, is condemned under pretence of having exceeded his Maſter's Orders, in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſſports for the Exportation of Money and Corn. But hereſy was the capital Accuſation that was laid to his Charge. Nevertheleſs the Author aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, <hi>That the Impeachment againſt him was grounded particularly, upon ſeveral Letters that were found among his Papers, wherein he acknowledged that he held pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Correſpondences with the Princes of</hi> Germany. <hi>unknown to the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in regard that Hiſtory is but a Texture of Original Letters, and that every Politician has his particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon an Affair which he does not well underſtand, no wonder that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> repreſents ſo variouſly the Deſigns and Inclinations of thoſe who had the greateſt Share in that Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He ſays, <hi>That</hi> Francis I. <hi>was weary at laſt of the Capriccio's of</hi> Henry VIII. <hi>and conſented to the definitive Sentence, which condemned him to retake his Wiſe under Pain of Excommunication.</hi> Nevertheleſs he obſerves, that after that Sentence, <hi>Francis</hi> I. ſided with <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. in all his Affairs with all the Zeal imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>That</hi> Francis I. <hi>would not hear the Propoſal of</hi> Clement VII. <hi>That that Pope had promiſed before to do for the King of</hi> England <hi>all that lay in his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: That the Pope made ſome Scruple at it, but at length gave him his Promiſe.</hi> But all theſe new Promiſes could not make the Holy Father forget thoſe that he had made at the beginning of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to the General of the <hi>Cordeliers,</hi> the Emperor's Agent. <hi>Clement</hi> himſelf acknowledged that he had promiſed that he would never pronounce Sentence upon the Divorce, and that he would do nothing in that Affair without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Charles</hi> I. Notice. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be ſo exceſſively tied to Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> on the other ſide, is as little tied to Promiſes. And therefore we muſt confeſs that the Complaiſance of that Church goes ſometimes a very great way. <hi>In thoſe Ages,</hi> ſaith our Author, ſpeaking of thoſe that followed the <hi>Tenth, The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline touching Marriages was not ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57293:3"/>ſevere as afterwards. Kings put away their Wives upon ſlight occaſions, and never ſought for any Pretence. Afterwards they were deſirous to have one, and it was as eaſie to find one; becauſe they could not marry with a Kinſwoman on this ſide the Seventh Degree: So that Princes that could not allie themſelves indifferently with all ſorts of Perſons finding themſelves all united in Blood, and coming to diſlike their match, proved there near affinity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> away their Wives and took others. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> there were ſome Princes who had Two or Three Wives living, and Princeſſes that had Two or Three Husbands. This was practiſed in the Tenth, Eleventh, Twelfth and Thirteenth Ages; and in theſe times of Darkneſs and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance it was, that theſe Sholes of Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts and Scholaſtick Divines became ſo numerous.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter to Monſieur <hi>Thevenot,</hi> being a full Refutation of Mr. <hi>Le Grand</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>HENRY</hi> VIII<hi>'s</hi> Divorcing <hi>KATHARINE</hi> of <hi>Arragon.</hi> With a plain Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame by Dr. <hi>G. B.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PErmit me, Sir, before I pay you all thoſe marks of Reſpect which are your due, to aſſure you that I am ſo well perſwaded of your Probity and Sincerity, that maugre the difference of perſwaſion that is between us, nevertheleſs I dare adventure to ſubmit to your Judgment in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that ſeems to be between me and M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> in a matter that has no ſmall relation to Religion. Opinions, and the ſpeculative Conſequences whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Men draw from matters of Fact, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very much different, according to the different Idea's which Men have of the Things: But the matters of Fact themſelves have but one Face, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves after the ſame manner to all that ſeek the Truth. Therefore in regard that our diſpute moves alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon matters of Fact, I am apt to believe I can hazard nothing in taking you for my Arbitrator.</p>
               <p>During our laſt Reſidence at <hi>Paris,</hi> having had the Honour to viſit you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, I had time to obſerve with how much juſtice you made your ſelf the ſubject, and the eſteem, and admiration of all the World. I was convinced of it more particularly by the Civilities which you heap'd upon me, and by the pains you took to bring me into a Conference with M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> in your own and the Preſence of M. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zout.</hi> I was the leſs ſcrupulous when I found my ſelf in a place where I could expect nothing but fair dealing from a perſon that lived in the Houſe of a Man no leſs conſiderable for his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Vertues, than for the great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments with which he was entruſted, and who frequently converſed with the Learned M. <hi>Bulteau,</hi> who as often viſited the famous M. <hi>Baluze,</hi> whoſe Sincerity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57293:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>equals his profound Learning, a thing rarely to be found in our Age: And, which was more than all the reſt, a Friend of <hi>M. Thevenot</hi>'s. This made me look upon M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> as a perſon that had all thoſe noble Qualities that were to be expected from a fair Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary.</p>
               <p>I ſhould give you too great a trouble to recal to your memories all thoſe little Things that were upheld in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, and at which you your ſelves were ſo much diſtated, that you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd ingeniouſly how much you <hi>were aſhamed</hi> to hear them. You made this acknowledgment not only to me, after M. <hi>Le Grand</hi>'s departure, but to ſeveral others alſo; and you were ſo well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in this, that though what had been propounded, was not worth the talking of, yet that I had fully anſwer'd the Diſcourſe, as mean and frivolous as it was. M. <hi>Auzout</hi> deſired likewiſe at the ſame time, that I would make no noiſe of it, to which requeſt I was readily induced to condeſcend: For to ſay the very truth, I did not find that my Adverſary was a ſubject worthy my Triumph, or the pains of boaſting in publick a Victory over him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as to what I have deem'd requiſite to inſert of our Diſcourſe, among the Remarks which I have made upon ſome paſſages of the Hiſtory of M. <hi>Varillas,</hi> I have managed M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> with all the Circumſpection that he could expect from me. Though, if in the purſuit of this Diſcourſe, I happen to wound him more to the quick, he muſt thank himſelf, and not lay the blame on any body elſe.</p>
               <p>I can eaſily brook all thoſe Reflections which he has made <hi>upon my Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>ſhallowneſs of Capacity,</hi> more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly upon what he ſays, <hi>That I never ſtudied the Hiſtory or the Laws of</hi> England. For thus he expreſſes himſelf after he had beſtowed great Praiſes upon me, and ſuch as I never deſerved. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, by the ſuddain change of his Pen, he ſeems to look upon me as a Perſon of little worth. But that ſame Thick skull'd, and common Artifice of ſome People to praiſe thoſe whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation they have a deſign to deſtroy will never ſurprize men of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nor will hainous and dirty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches paſs among them under the Covert of a few generous Encomium's. I muſt be contented with that ſmall meaſure of Knowledge and Capacity, which come to my juſt ſhare, eſpecially now that I have to do with a perſon of ſo mean a Talent, as M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be by this ſame Treatiſe of his.</p>
               <p>I could only wiſh that they, who would be better inform'd of the truth of that celebrated Paſſage of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is the Subject of our Diſpute, would give themſelves the trouble to read what <hi>Sanders</hi> and my ſelf have written, and then peruſe the Hiſtory of M. <hi>Le Grand.</hi> I am aſſur'd they will conclude, That there muſt be ſome fault in the Title Page, where he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes the <hi>Defence of</hi> Sanders, <hi>and the Refutation of the Two firſt Books of my Hiſtory.</hi> The whole ſubſtance of his Work agrees altogether with mine, unleſs it be in ſome parts, where he ſhews that <hi>great Art</hi> of his, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rein I yield him willingly to out-do me. In all things elſe he ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly concurrs with me, that I am tempted to believe, He only took his Pen in hand, to fulfil thoſe Offers which he made me in your Preſence, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57293:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>me with <hi>Memoirs</hi> ſufficient for the Confirmation of what I have wrote upon this Subject. True it is, I have not read any more as yet than the Firſt Part of his Book; nor can I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine how he can juſtifie <hi>Sanders,</hi> whom he has abandon'd during the whole courſe of his Hiſtory. He forſakes him in the whole Hiſtory of <hi>Ann of Boloigne,</hi> and in all the progreſſes of the Story that depends upon it, though it be the chief Head of <hi>Sanders</hi>'s Accuſation, and which he preſſes moſt vigorouſly, as being a Nullity in the Title of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and conſequently an Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pretence for Rebellion. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges alſo the <hi>Decretal Bull,</hi> nor does he inſiſt upon the Carriage of Sr. <hi>Thomas Moore.</hi> In a word, if you exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Fourſcore Faults of which I have accus'd <hi>Sanders</hi> in my Additions, you will find that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed above Seventy, and confirms what I have maintained in oppoſition to him. Which will moſt evidently appear, if his work ſhall ever be thought worthy a larger Examination.</p>
               <p>I ſay nothing of his Stile, for that his Readers without much conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſtudy will eaſily find it to be the Stile rather of an Advocate that pleads a Cauſe, than of a perſon diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted, that cordially and barely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates matter of Fact. For to argue with heat and paſſion, and reproach his Adverſaries, are unpardonable faults in an Hiſtorian. Beſides that, there is ſomething ſo ſacred in the very Aſhes of Kings, that they are never to be ſpok'n of but with great Caution; and if at any time there be an unavoidable occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to blame ſome of their Actions, ſofter Terms are to be made uſe of, than thoſe of <hi>Lye</hi> and <hi>Impoſture.</hi> Add to this, that the principal Point, and upon which the whole Queſtion moves, being, Whether the King's own Cauſe ought not rather to be judged in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and by his Clergy, than at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Conſiſtory; that man can never be thought to act conformably to the Gallican Church, who takes part with the Pope upon this occaſion. It is rather to be wondered at, that at a time when there is ſo little reſpect given at <hi>Verſailles</hi> to the <hi>Vatican</hi> Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and where the ancient Cuſtom is renewed of appealing from the Pope to the General Council; I ſay, it is a wonder, at ſuch a time as this, a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this nature, ſhould not be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with more freedom and ſincerity. Perhaps this is one of the little Tricks of thoſe ſort of People, which <hi>M. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> has more frankly deſcribed, than I have a deſign to do, who make hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous portraictures of the Actions of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. to obſerve the glory of thoſe of <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi> And perhaps our Author is neither ſo great a Politician, nor ſo well knowing in Affairs, as to have ſuch diſtant proſpects in his Eyes, or elſe this work being his firſt Eſſay, he did not ſtudy the Point with that Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication which was requiſite, believing that trouble to no purpoſe while he has to do with a perſon, <hi>that gives no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> proofs of his Underſtanding than my ſelf. I ſhall therefore inſiſt only upon ſix of his principal Errors, which are nothing to the great number of miſtakes which he has committed, and which I could eaſily make appear, had I the Liberty to enlarge my ſelf in a writing that muſt be inſerted into the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57293:4"/>
               <p n="1">I. He calls in queſtion the Contents of the Decretal Bull, which Cardinal <hi>Campeggio</hi> brought, upon this Ground, That having been only ſhewn to the King and Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> no Body can tell what it was; and if it had been a definitive Sentence in that matter, the Legates Commiſſion had been at an end, and the King would have contracted his Second Marriage, as formerly <hi>Lewis</hi> the XII. did, without expecting any other proceedings.</p>
               <p>Had Monſieur <hi>Le Grand</hi> given himſelf the trouble to read that Bull which I have publiſhed, he might have ſpar'd himſelf ſo many uſeleſs Remarks. The Bull was contriv'd in <hi>England</hi> and ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> where, though ſome few Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations were made, it appeared ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs by all the Letters, that were written reciprocally from <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> that the Bull which was given to <hi>Compeggio</hi> was in ſubſtance the ſame. Certain it is, that Bull declared the King's Pretences to be juſt, gave power to the Legates, to examine the Truth of them, and to pronounce Sentence upon the proofs that ſhould be made before them. For though this Bull implied a definitive Sentence of the Pope, upon a ſuppoſition of the Validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King's Pretenſions; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it left many things for the Legates to do. They were to inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<list>
                     <item>1. Whether the King had not deſired this Marriage himſelf.</item>
                     <item>2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it would not occaſion a War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> ſhould a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation be granted.</item>
                     <item>3. Whether this Diſpenſation had been annull'd by the Proteſtation which the King made againſt the Marriage, when he came to be of Age.</item>
                     <item>4. Whether any of the Princes, in favour of whom the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was allow'd, were Dead before the Marriage was conſummated.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>It is apparent that that ſame Bull for the diſſolution of the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Catharine,</hi> being only granted upon ſuppoſition, that all the matters in Queſtion were as the King maintained them to be, had been void in caſe he could not have prov'd his ſuggeſtions; which is the thing that confounds all the Author's Arguments.</p>
               <p>But I muſt confeſs that M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> has ſomething of Reaſon on his ſide in what he ſays concerning <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> whom I believed to have been <hi>Campeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio</hi>'s <hi>Baſtard.</hi> He proves out of <hi>Sigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> who writes the Life of that Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, that <hi>Rodulphus</hi> was his Legitimate Son. <hi>Sigonius</hi> is a very good Author, and I acquieſce in his Authority. But had M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> caſt but his Eyes upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Edition, he would have ſeen that it was not without <hi>ſufficient Ground,</hi> and not out of any deſign to <hi>blacken the Reputation</hi> of C. <hi>Campeggio,</hi> that I call'd <hi>Rodulphus</hi> Baſtard; ſince I quote the very Diſcourſe wherein he is ſo called, which was Compos'd by Sr. <hi>William Thomas,</hi> Secretary to the Privy Council, under the Title of the <hi>Engliſh Pilgrim.</hi> I had the misfortune not to have ſeen the Life that was written by <hi>Sigonius,</hi> ſo that it is only a fault of Omiſſion, which the Author would aggravate into a malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Invention. And I make this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of my Error ſo much the more frankly, becauſe it is the only miſtake among all the reſt of which the Author accuſes me, that is well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="2">II. M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> labours to deſtroy the Authority of the Deciſion of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57293:5"/>
                  <hi>Sorbom</hi> in favour of <hi>Henry.</hi> But in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard this Deciſion was printed the Year following, and acknowledged for true and real, ſince no perſon in thoſe times taxes it of being counterfeited, we have no reaſon now to ſuſpect it; for neither does Cardinal <hi>Poole,</hi> who was then at <hi>Paris,</hi> when it was made, nor any other writer of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, tax the King of Impoſture upon that occaſion. Add to this that the Biſhop of <hi>Tarbes</hi> being continued to ſollicit in <hi>Henry</hi>'s behalf at the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> after he was made Cardinal, and that the King had publickly acknowledged before the Legates, how privy that Prelate had been to his Scruples con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon his Marriage, has given an undeniable Confirmation of this matter, whatever our Author ſays to the contrary. The ſame thing is to be ſaid of the <hi>Sorbonn;</hi> for that never having been charged with falſhood in the particular of this Deciſion, there is no queſtion but that they made it. So that all M. <hi>Le Grana</hi>'s Arguments can never prove any thing more, than only that it has occaſioned great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, and that <hi>Beda</hi> was a real pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of Sedition. By the way, we may obſerve that the Eccleſiaſticks of <hi>France</hi> were very ill ſatisfied with the Conduct of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, who had ſold their Liberties by the <hi>Concordate,</hi> of which the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> was ſo ſenſible, and for that reaſon full of Male-contents. And therefore it might be perhaps that ſo many of the <hi>French</hi> Clergy were ſo ill affected to <hi>Henry</hi>'s Cauſe, becauſe they knew that <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt ſo paſſionately ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Intereſts. After all, the Author confeſſes, That he ſound in the ſcrutiny Fifty three voices for the Divorce, and Forty two againſt it; and Five, that were of Opinion that the matter ſhould be referr'd to the Pope. And this is ſufficient to juſtifie the printed Deciſion, which only ſays, That the greateſt number of Doctors were for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce, and declared the Marriage ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, which may ſerve for an Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words of the Letter of the firſt Preſident, <hi>That that ſame Declaration would do the King more hurt than it would advance his Affairs;</hi> In regard all the other Univerſities had judged in his Favour, whereas the Opinion of the <hi>Sorbonn</hi> favour'd him only by the plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of voices.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The Author, who pretends to publiſh an Extract of the Reaſons which the Favourers of <hi>Henry</hi> alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Marriage, has forgot the Principal, and that which ſupported all the deciſions of the Romiſh Church; that is to ſay, <hi>That the Scripture, explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Tradition, is the Rule according to which all Controverſies are to be determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> They alledged a perpetual ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Provincial and general Councils, of Popes, and the Chief of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers; particularly, the Four moſt famous Fathers of the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Church, whereas the Imperialiſts had neither Father nor Doctor on their ſide. Nevertheleſs the Author ſays no more, but that the Engliſh quoted the Canons of ſome Provincial Councils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Incontinency; with certain paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom</hi> about Virginity, and againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Nuptials. I am ſure the Reader muſt here take notice, That there is ſomething wanting in this Relation which is more eſſential to an honeſt Man,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57293:5"/>than a great ſtock of <hi>Capacity.</hi> For the Canons of Councils and the Paſſages out of the Fathers which they quoted, ſpeak expreſly of the Degrees of Marriage, forbidden in <hi>Leviticus.</hi> He names Three Popes whoſe Letters they produced; but he paſſes over in ſilence the Chief, in reference to <hi>England,</hi> who was <hi>Gregory the Great.</hi> For the Saxons being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted at what time he held the See, this Pope gave expreſs Order to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> the Monk to diſannul all Marriages that had been contracted with Brothers Wives. Now <hi>England</hi> having ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Law, upon its firſt embracing Chriſtianity, they who defended the Kings ſcruples looked upon this as the Principal Foundation of his Cauſe. So that if M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> would have acquired the Reputation of a ſincere Hiſtorian, he ought to have mentioned this Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Moreover he ſhould not have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over in ſilence as he does, all that was alledged againſt the Power which the Popes aſſume to themſelves of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with all Eccleſiaſtical, and every the Divine Laws themſelves. Nor ought he to have forgot that other great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon urged by the King, that according to the Canons of the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> the determination of that matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed of right to the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> and not to the Pope. If the Author be a True Member of the <hi>Gallican Church,</hi> he ought to grant theſe Maximes; and if he would be thought a Faithful Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, he ought not to paſs them over in ſilence. But though he do not ſet down all the Kings Reaſons, he adds ſeveral New Reaſons to the Queens pleading, which her Advocates never dream'd of, and we do not meet with in any Story or Relation of that time. They all tend to prove that the Rules touching the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Conſanguinity have not been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways obſerved in Marriages with the ſame Exactneſs. But the Church is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by Rules and not by Examples.</p>
               <p>As for the Law of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> which permitts a Man to Marry his Siſter-in-Law, if her Husband died without Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it has been always conſidered in the Chriſtian Church, as an Exception to the General Rule; ſo that in regard it was only made in favour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and with reference to their Right of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was aboliſh'd together with their Republick; whereas the Laws of <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> concerning this Matter, are to be look'd upon as Laws that are Moral and Univerſally received. In a word if you will take the pains to compare the Books that have been written upon this Subject, with the Extracts which M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> and my ſelf have given of them, you will preſently find that he writes with no Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity at all, who deſcends to a Nicety. For my part I ſhall not Envy him the High Opinion he has of his, ſo long as Men will but acknowledge me to have writ ſincerely and without the Byaſs of Intereſt.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Our Author ſays that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboliſh'd the Oath which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſwore to the Pope at the time of their Conſecration; and form'd another which they were to ſwear to the King. But this is not that which he calls under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the Bottom, the Laws and Hiſtory of <hi>England.</hi> For the Truth was this. They read in that Aſſembly the two oaths which the Biſhops took, the one to the Pope, the other to the King; and in regard they found them to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57293:6"/>Contradictory, as being two oaths of Homage and Fidelity, which could only be ſworn to one Soveraign; they abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd that which was made to the Pope, and let that ſtand in it's full vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour which was ſworn to the King. I have given an undeniable Example of their oaths ſworn to the King by the Biſhops in former Ages, which is to be ſeen in an Act at the head of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the Pieces that juſtifie my Hiſtory. If M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> had only the <hi>French Tranſlation,</hi> where thoſe Pieces are not, he might have conſulted the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Edition at Mr. <hi>Bulteau's,</hi> where they are all to be ſeen. He might have there ſeen in the Act which I cite, <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Adrian</hi> renounce not only all the Clauſes of the Bulls which were contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Kings Prerogative, or the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> but alſo ſwear an Oath of Fealty to the King, in the ſame Terms which our Kings have ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to receive them from the Biſhops. The Oath to the Pope, which is an Innovation not known till before the XII. Age, contains beſides, ſo many large and unlimited Clauſes, which neither accord with the Doctrine of the Gallican Church, nor with that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and duty which Prelates owe their lawful Prince, ſince it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently an Oath of Homage and Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to a Foreign Power.</p>
               <p n="5">V. Mr. <hi>Le Grand</hi> labours might and main, to make <hi>Cranmer</hi> to be look'd upon as one of the moſt wicked men in the world. He accuſes me for making him a Gentleman, but I have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, though I well knew him to be ſo; not believing that Quality con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable enough to be mentioned in the Eulogies due to the memory of ſo great a Perſonage. He cannot believe, <q>That <hi>Cranmer</hi> was in <hi>Germany</hi> when <hi>Warham</hi> died, nor that he was named in his Abſence to be Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury;</hi> nor that he ſtay'd Seven weeks after he received the News of his Nomination, becauſe he aſſiſted at the Marriage of the King with <hi>Anne Bolen.</hi>
                  </q> He cannot allow what I ſay, <q>That this Affair went on ſlowly, ſince it was but three Months between <hi>December</hi> and <hi>January</hi> before this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late was known to be exalted at <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor will he be perſwaded, That the Provincial Synod of <hi>Canterbury</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced any poſitive ſentence upon the Marriage of the King.</q> See here more miſtakes than <hi>Varillas</hi> himſelf could have been guilty of. For in the Criminal Proceſs againſt <hi>Cranmer</hi> which is Printed, we find that he calls his Judges to witneſs, with what reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he accepted the Primacy of <hi>England;</hi> and that he did not return out of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> till Seven Weeks after the King had ſignified to him his Intentions. Nor did the Biſhops who knew his Judges, and who had been Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his behaviour at that time, ſay any thing to it, as not being able to contradict what he ſaid. Twelve Weeks paſſed from the Twenty third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> that <hi>Warham</hi> died, to the Fourteenth of <hi>November,</hi> that the King was married; ſo that although the Courrier had ſtaid Fifteen days by the way, <hi>Cranmer</hi> might have delay'd his departure for Seven Weeks, and yet have come time enough to be at the Nuptials of the King. But our Author to change Five Months into three ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57293:6"/>
                  <hi>September</hi> and <hi>January</hi> out of his Account, for this only Reaſon, That he found it requiſite to retrench them. As for the Judgment of the Synod of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Sentence of Divorce has it in expreſs Terms, That the two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Synods of <hi>England</hi> had decided the King's Cauſe.</p>
               <p>But M. <hi>Le Grand,</hi> above all things makes it a Crime in <hi>Cranmer,</hi> that he took an Oath of Obedience to the Pope when he was conſecrated; and for that he made a Proteſtation, by which he gave divers Reſtrictions to the ſaid Oath. But he reports all that he ſays concerning this Matter, upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of certain paſſionate Scriblers, and quite contrary to the Faith of the publick Acts. The Proteſtation of the Archbiſhop was read twice before the Altar, while he was conſecrating, and it is clear that he had no deſign to make uſe of Equivocals, ſince what he did, he did in publick, and for that the Biſhops uſually made Proteſtations, by which they renounced all Clauſes of their Bulls which were contrary to the Kings Prerogative. It ſeems the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, accuſtomed to this doubling Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, had ſo much Power over <hi>Cranmer</hi> as to encline him to take the Oath, and reſtrain it by a publick Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, made at the ſame time; ſo that if he did any thing amiſs in ſo doing; it was rather a Defect of Judgment in that Prelate, than any want of Sincerity.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. The Author ſays that the King pardoned <hi>Moore</hi> and <hi>Fiſher,</hi> the Buſineſs <hi>of the Maid of</hi> Kent; and though he confeſs that the firſt ridicules her for an <hi>idle ſilly Nun</hi> in one of his Letters, yet he ſeems not to have ſeen a long Letter of <hi>Moore</hi>'s, which I publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my juſtifying Pieces belonging to the Second Volume, where he ſpeaks of the pretended Revelations of that religious Wench, <hi>as one of the moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Impoſtures that ever were.</hi> As for <hi>Fiſher,</hi> whatever the Author ſays, he was condemned for favouring that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture. To this M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> adds, <hi>That the Chancellour having demanded of</hi> Fiſher <hi>and</hi> Moore, <hi>what they thought of the Statues made in the laſt Parliament, they would make no Anſwer, only they ſaid, That being cut off from civil Society, they minded nothing but their Meditation upon their Saviour's Paſſion, which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer coſt them their Lives.</hi> Here is a Corruption of Hiſtory, which I ſhall not call ſo bad as it deſerves; which is ſo much the more odious, for that writing things as they were tranſacted, and according to publick Acts, he could repreſent them after a manner ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to his own Cauſe. Theſe two great Men were condemned at firſt by virtue of a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> which is loſs of Goods and perpetual Impriſonment, for having refuſed to take the Oath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Succeſſion, by reaſon of the Kings Marriage according to an Act of Parliament. After that they were far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſecuted, becauſe they oppoſed the King's Supremacy, or his Title of the ſupreme Head of the Engliſh Church. There is one thing too in <hi>Moore</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs which might be ſufficient to make a Man Guilty of High Treaſon, where he ſays, <hi>That a Parliament can both make a King and depoſe a King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now In regard I have conſin'd myſelf within theſe Six Heads, I ſhall go no farther; but the abundance of Matter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57293:7"/>makes me that I have much ado to hold here, I cannot but wonder the Author has forgot ſo many important Things in his Hiſtory, and that he could find in the Collection of Letters printed by <hi>Camuzat,</hi> which I never ſaw, until he did me the Honour to give them unto me. He ſays nothing of what the Pope promiſed Cardinal <hi>Tournon, That for Forms Sake he ſhould be obliged to obſerve ſome Formalities of Action, to the End he might not ſhew himſelf too partial to the King of</hi> England, <hi>in favour of whom he was reſolved to do what lay in his Power, for the Love of you,</hi> ſaid the Prelate, writing to the King of <hi>France.</hi> And a little after, <hi>I think I am well aſſured that our Holy Father will comply with you, touching the Requeſt which you have made him in Behalf of your ſaid Brother,</hi> Henry VIII. In a Letter of the Seventeenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1533. The ſame Cardinal writes to <hi>Francis</hi> I. <hi>That the greateſt Party of the Cardinals, that were of the Imperial Faction, would have been mad with the Pope, had he not done what he did, in regard there was but little likely-hood that the King would ſubmit his Cauſe, and that the Pope might have ſome honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Pretence to act for him, he would do it with as good a Will as was poſſible. And it may be,</hi> adds this Miniſter, <hi>when you meet together</hi> (he ſpeaks of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview that was to be at <hi>Marſeilles</hi>) <hi>there will be found out Expedients.</hi> It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo by another Letter, that <hi>Francis</hi> I. told the Engliſh Embaſſador, <hi>That the Pope himſelf had confeſſed that King</hi> Henry<hi>'s Cauſe was juſt, and that he wanted nothing but a Procuration.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was that when the King was cited to appear at <hi>Rome</hi> in Perſon, or by a Proctor, he took little Notice of it. That if <hi>Carne</hi> were ſent beyond the Mountains in the Quality of an <hi>Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> it was ſeen by thoſe Mixtures that it was not in the Name of the King, but in the Nation's Behalf that he went to make thoſe kind of Excuſes.</p>
               <p>This Refuſal of <hi>Henry</hi> being look'd upon at <hi>Rome</hi> as an effect of Contempt, which he had of the Holy See, the Pope promiſed him the Divorce if he would but appear in that City either in Perſon or by his Proctor, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Aſſignation which he had cauſed to be given him, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his Authority. <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt applauded the King's Conduct in that Affair, and was ſo far from endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to oppoſe his Marriage, that he ordered his Embaſſador to be God-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Name to the Child that ſhould be born in caſe it were a Son. The <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador at <hi>Rome</hi> about that time wrote alſo ſeveral Letters to his Maſter's Court, where he obſerves, <hi>That the Pope was very ready to do what was deſired in the King of</hi> England<hi>'s behalf, and more if he durſt or could, but that the Emperors People preſſed the Affair with ſo much Importunity, that the half of the time, His Holineſs, againſt God and againſt Reaſon, nay, contrary to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of a good part of the Imperial Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, was conſtrained above half the time, to act at the pleaſure of M.</hi> Doſme — <hi>We wanted you there to have put a spoak in his Wheel,</hi> purſues he, writing to the Cardinal of <hi>Grandemont, There is no Man that dares tell him the Truth.</hi> And it is as true that this Embaſſador who was Biſhop of <hi>Auxerres,</hi> ſaid alſo ſpeaking to the Pope, <hi>That he ſaw him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57293:7"/>ſo preſſed by the Emperor, his People, and the greateſt part of the Cardinals, that he thought he could do no good but only by Diſſimulation.</hi> But indeed theſe cunning Politicians underſtand ſo well how to change their Stile, according to Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences, that there's hardly any truſt to be given to their Letters. The ſame Day that he wrote what we have cited to the Pope's Legate, in another Letter to the Grand Maſter he obſerves, that the Pope had told him, that for Four Years the <hi>Buſineſs of</hi> Henry <hi>VIII. had been in his Hands, that there was nothing effected as yet; that if he might do what he would, he would do what we would;</hi> and ſays the Miniſter, <hi>This he told me in ſuch a manner, that if I am not deceived he thought what he ſpoke.</hi> All thoſe Letters were dated the 17. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1532. But in another of the 13. of <hi>Jan.</hi> following, he aſſures that the Pope had told him, <hi>That he was reſolved to referr the whole Buſineſs to a good Time;</hi> and that he clearly underſtood, <hi>what the Pope meant by a good Time.</hi> To which he adds, that if the Matter had been judged accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Wiſhes of the Cardinals, and the eager Inſtances of the Emperor's People, the moſt ancient and learned had judged for the King of <hi>England.</hi> But that there were but few of that Company, and the number of the other was ſo great, that by plurality of voices the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would have utterly loſt it.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> is very nice and tender, when he comes to that Circumſtance, that there arriv'd a Courrier from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> a day or two after Sentence was given; and he omits the haſt in which it was pronounced, as if he knew nothing of it. Nevertheleſs we find in theſe Miſcellanies, a Letter from <hi>Pomponio Trivulci,</hi> dated from <hi>Lyons</hi> the 16. of <hi>April,</hi> where he obſerves, that M. <hi>de Paris</hi> paſſing that way upon his return from <hi>Rome,</hi> told him that the definitive Sentence which the Pope had given againſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> had been precipitated. That it was not the Pope's fault that they did not tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porize longer; that if they had ſtaid but Six Days more before they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced it, the King would have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>to the Holy See. But that the Importunity of the Imperaliſts and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory was ſo great, that they would not ſtay. That the next Day after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of</hi> England <hi>came too late, but that then the Conſiſtory and the Imperaliſts were mad, that they ſtaid no longer.</hi> All theſe paſſages plainly ſhew, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was governed in this Affair, only by the proſpects and maxims of Policy. And therefore it is, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Principles of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, M. <hi>Talon</hi> has maintained with ſo much Zeal, upon an occaſion of much leſs importance, that the King of <hi>England</hi> had no reaſon to have any regard to the Sentences and Thundrings of that Court.</p>
               <p>If I am extreamly obliged to M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> for having made me a preſent of ſo good a Book, in which he furniſh'd me with ſo many proofs of the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Points of my Hiſtory, I am no leſs troubled that he had ſo little value for himſelf, as to ſuppreſs them, and for his having forced me, as I may ſo ſay, to make uſe of the kindneſs he has done me to his own diſadvantage. But upon ſuch occaſions as theſe, they ſaying is,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57293:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Magis amica veritas.</hi> And though M. <hi>Le Grand</hi> imagines that <hi>I am jealous</hi> of my <hi>Productions,</hi> were not the Intereſts of Religion intermixed therewith, I could eaſily abandon mine. But I will not now puſh this cenſure any farther; neither do I know whether I ſhall write any more upon this Subject, not being able to determine any thing in that matter, till I have ſeen the Three other parts of this work, and the effects it will produce in the World. I ſhall conclude with humble requeſt to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Liberty which I take of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing this Letter to you, and that in ſo publick a manner, not believing a man could otherwiſe ſo properly give a cenſure upon a printed Book.</p>
               <closer>I am, <salute>Sir,</salute> &amp;c. 
<dateline>
                     <hi>Hague,</hi> 
                     <date>20. of <hi>June.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:57293:8"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
